If you're a personal trainer,
you should be very excited because your
job fucking
sucks.
You start work earlier than anyone else in
the world.
Then you're to go to work,
then take a break, then go back to work,
then take a
break for a few hours,
then come back to work
when everyone else has left work,
then get home late in the evening,
barely get any sleep,
come back to work again.
Can you imagine if I had a job application
out?
"Hey, I want to pay you okay money.
You're going to start work at 6:00 a.m.,
have
three lunch breaks,
and get home at 7:00 p.m.
Oh, and by the way, your entire workday
is one-to-one meetings, and every
single person expects you to be at their
best." You'd be like, "No, I'm not doing
that." But you love fitness
and the idea of going to work in
activewear, so you
decide to do the job. My name
is James Smith.
I have done thousands of hours of personal
training.
I've built one of the biggest fitness
empires, had hundreds of thousand people
using my coaching app,
and also became a "Sunday Times" number
one best-selling
author and broke a lot of records in the
nonfiction publishing
space in fitness.
So you're probably thinking,
"That sounds awful." Well, let me
tell you this.
What a lot of you don't realize as
personal trainers is you probably
won't do this job forever,
and the lessons you're going to learn from
growing and
operating a fitness business,
you will take with you into the next thing
you do.
But before we get into that,
let me give you some tips
that I wish someone had come
along and told me 10 years ago. Now,
one of the most amazing things
is to become a
personal trainer,
you don't actually have to be
that skilled or that expertised.
Expertise? Just made that up. To begin,
you just need to be enthusiastic because a
lot of people actually just need a
cheerleader. Sounds crazy, but they do.
They need someone in their corner because
they're going through some kind of
transformative process in their life.
Chances are their husband
or their wife doesn't really give a shit,
and actually
the better they do getting fit
and healthy actually makes their husband
or wife
kind of resent them a bit.
That's why they are often the diet
saboteurs.
They're the ones, "Oh, babe,
just have a bit of chocolate.
Relax." Because the leaner their partner
gets, the more it makes them feel like
shit. Now,
another beautiful thing with your business
is it can be
hybrid. You can have clients in person and
online. You can do a mixture of both,
and as you get better at building your
online
brand,
you can just do less hours in person.
You can pick every single hour
that you want to work.
You can pick how much you charge.
You can pick the days you work.
So although there
are some pretty terrible parts to running
a business business,
should you do it right,
you actually don't run a PT business,
you run a lifestyle
business.
Because you're not going to make 100
million a year as a PT, but you
can make significantly more than the
average person and have a whole lot of
freedom
to do it. Now, it's important
that you identify your business sits
within two
components, in person and online.
Now, if we were to draw how this
is going to look over probably the next
three
months, this one,
nothing's going to happen for a very long
period of time.
Then you can start to see an uptick.
In person goes the other way,
wherein literally day one,
you can get yourself some
clients, and over the next few months,
as you get people working with you online,
you can start to dial down the amount of
sessions that you're doing.
Then this part, if we put these together,
this is the meta that we are aiming for,
where we decrease the amount we're doing
in person, and we increase the amount
we're doing online.
You might be wondering why I'm calling
that the meta.
Well, the reason that we love
that part so much is that is your
ability to scale.
Not many businesses have the ability to
scale within a handful of
months. That's why this period
is so magical.
If you are a plumber
or a landscape gardener or
a vet, you have to do years in the trade,
then you would have to make
strategic hires,
then you'd have to get a facility,
then there'd be loads of legal
red tape and other things
that you'd have to jump through.
And in other professions,
it takes so much time to get there
that as a personal
trainer,
in the period of time it takes other
people to get qualified, you've
already scaled your business. And
when I say scale,
the thing I'm trying to allude
to is to begin with you work money for
time.
One hour costs X. But when you go online,
you can service clients
in a much quicker period of time.
You can get help. You can get assistance.
You can hire other coaches.
And as I've said in a lot of videos
before, a lot of
personal trainers,
coaches don't realize that
when you build a brand and a
business online using social media,
you are effectively working in the stock
market, but within that stock market,
you are able to influence the
trade price on a daily basis.
You can get away with insider trading.
That's why it's a very exciting time
[chuckles] for any of you.
Okay, now, the thing
that you need to appreciate to begin with,
that client
acquisition is different. Now,
very quickly, let's start with in person.
Oh, and by the way, this sucks,
and the majority of people that don't like
in-person prospecting,
it's because you're a fucking pussy
and you probably haven't
worked that hard, and chances
are you're probably Gen Z.
So let me tell you on a quick little
story.
Back in the day,
I used to work in door-to-door sales.
People used to tell me to fuck off.
Then I worked in a call center,
100 calls a
day. People tell me to fuck off.
I had to work as a
laborer on a building site where they gave
me shit jobs. I pretty much ate shit.
I even worked in a shopping center having
to stop people whilst they're doing their
shopping to try and sell them stuff.
So when I came to the gym
and I could approach people that
are trying to work
towards a goal,
where a huge percentage of them don't know
what they're doing and
they're scared and they all need help,
coming to this as a first job, I can
appreciate why a lot of people go, "Ugh,
it's really hard.
Ugh, but people might say no."
When you come from door-to-door sales,
this is
great, brother. Everyone
is giving you little hints and tips
and tricks
about the problems they're facing by the
equipment that they're on.
But the thing is,
you don't need to go up to them
and be like, "Hey, I'm a personal
trainer." Just be fucking helpful.
Has it ever occurred to you
that on this YouTube channel,
for literally the last
few years,
I've just been putting out free nuggets of
information
to the majority of people
and getting nothing in return?
I would say, no,
I can tell you 96% of people
that watch this
channel have never bought my shit. 96%.
But do you think I'm getting annoyed about
that?
Maybe a little bit because the vein's
coming out of my neck.
But ultimately,
if 96% of people in the gym aren't
interested in your stuff,
that means 4% are.
So that means if you approach 100 people,
whoever's fucking alarm that is, I'm
going to knock someone out in a second.
You talk to people.
You got thousands of members in the gym.
You only need 10 clients in person to do
well.
So let's say you do 30 hours a week,
which by the way,
is the kind of ceiling that
we want to set for personal training
because anything more than 30 hours,
you're
going to be fucked.
You're going to be fucked.
Every time you hit 30 hours,
you put your prices up.
Then your hours come down a bit.
You walk for a little bit more Voila.
If you have 10 clients
and they see you twice a week each,
that's already
20 hours of coaching.
And then that's all you need to worry
about, because when
you're doing 20 hours of coaching on the
gym floor, people see you coaching all the
time,
and they'll just perceive you to be the
best, and they'll hire you. Okay?
So really,
you just need to work towards your first
10.
Then the thing you're thinking is,
how can I get people to train with me
twice a
week? They can only afford once. Well,
that's in your positioning.
Just before we get into the prospecting
bit, it's worth you saying to people, if
you were to say to your client, "Hey,
what do you want to do?" And they say, "I
want to learn to play the guitar."
If you say to them, "Hey,
it's going to take you
20 weeks doing it once a week,
or it's going to take 10 weeks doing it
twice a
week," they're probably going to opt for
the twice a week.
It's the way you position it. "Hey,
if you want to lose three kilograms of
fat, we
can either do it in 10 weeks or 20 weeks.
If you want to do it in 10 weeks,
you should see me twice." And also,
when you sell
people the blocks, just say,
"To begin with,
you've got to do two a week, and then
we'll drop down to one a week." Because
if they know in the future it's going to
become cheaper and it's going to be half
the price, they'll be more inclined to
agree to two a week to begin with.
And guess what?
Once they do it for two a week,
they often become accustomed to it,
and then they
say,
"Let's just keep it at two a week." Okay.
So very simply, you just chat to people,
you're just helpful to people.
Even right now,
I'm just making a video for personal
trainers.
If no one buys, that's okay.
And that's the attitude you have to have
to be
successful prospecting on the gym floor.
Someone eventually will inquire about
pricing, and you go, "Look, I don't talk
about pricing on the gym floor." Let's
have a sit down, go buy them a coffee, let
them just talk to you.
As a personal trainer,
you've got two ears and one mouth for
a reason. Just ask and ask and ask.
In the consultation,
get them to understand as
much as possible. Then say, "Hey,
I'm going to take you to the gym floor."
And when
you get to the gym floor, this
is what I used to always do.
I used to take them through exercises
that were incredibly difficult,
that didn't
require a lot of weight.
So I'd get them to squat,
get them to a hip hinge, get
them to move.
I'd get them to do a rear foot elevated
split squat, and then I would
show them ways I could make exercises
harder without exposing them to lots of
weight. Because they are worried
that you're just going to throw them in a
squat
rack, do loads of work, whatever.
And also,
a good personal trainer wants to get
the maximum response in stimulus from
their client whilst exposing them to the
minimal amount of fatigue possible.
Otherwise,
they'd just be doing TRX squat jumps.
Anyway, I digress.
Then once they realize
that your coaching method
is quite sensible,
you can then move to the close.
Because every personal trainer,
we all know it,
CrossFit PTs get their clients doing a
fucking workout of the
day.
The fucking physio PT gets them all doing
mobility shit.
The fucking jujitsu PT's got them butt
scooting on the ground, whatever it is.
But you just want to be able to show them
in that consultation session that you are
sensible. You go, "Hey, look. Right,
Amanda,
so that is a rear foot elevated split
squat. What I want you to do
is now I'm going to teach you a one
and a quarter.
The reason for this is, Amanda,
that as you get used to this stimulus,
I want to
make it harder,
but I don't want to load you with loads of
weight." And they go,
"Oh, that's quite nice,
actually." You show them your competence
and your
confidence around the gym floor,
then you sit them down afterwards
and you say,
"Look, if you want a one-off session,
it's 45 pounds.
But if you book 10 from me right now,
I'll do it for 300," which is still
undercharging. And then you go, "Look,
we could do it once or twice a week.
When that block runs out,
we can continue and look into it from
there.
But hey, Amanda,
just before you leave today,
just to let you know, if you don't
think my personal training
and the service that I offer you
is worth 10 times what
you pay let me know at any point over the
next 10 sessions.
If you're not happy,
I'll refund you in full." I did
that for 5,000 hours of
coaching over several years.
Only one person ever claimed their money
back, Laura,
and she was a bit of a bitch.
Yeah, Laura, you know who you are.
And it's very, very simple.
So let's say we talk to 100 people on the
gym floor.
96% of people aren't interested.
That's four clients per 100 people.
So that means if you speak to 250 people,
you've got a full book. Cool.
For the consultations,
I'm telling you now,
you'll close two out of three of those.
So you're looking to talking to 400
people, 500 people,
and you're fully booked.
And then you never really have to walk the
floor ever again.
Because, like I said, once you
are doing dozens of hours of personal
training on
the gym floor every single week,
people come to you because they
are watching you
with your client. And if you are sensible,
respectful, considerate,
curious, just good
and professional at what you do,
every hour you coach on the gym
floor is advertising for other people.
People go, "Oh, saw
that lady on the gym floor.
She looks great.
She's going to inquire." So really,
all I'm asking you to do to build a fully
fucking packed personal training business
in person is to talk to 500 people.
I did more than that in one fucking day of
door knocking or working in a
shopping center. Either you do
that work or don't
and fuck off back to recruitment at the
end of the day. Online is the tricky part.
It's not tricky, actually.
All you got to do is make videos.
I met with Meta, Facebook, last week,
and in essence, what they
said was use the edits app.
Let me show you something.
So my videos recently, the ones
that I film handheld from
my iPhone are doing so many more views,
645,000,
69,000, 194,000.
So you see this one here is
a professional one,
60, 194, 645, 138. Even this one here,
380,000.
There is a massive push at the moment for
user-generated content where you use your
phone, you film it, you edit it in
Instagram edits, and you post it.
Once you start getting busy as a personal
trainer,
you set up your camera in the corner,
you film yourself with a client, you
do voiceovers, you pick hooks,
you look for trends.
Get a little tripod like this.
You put your phone in it,
you start filming.
Then between clients,
you have a cancellation,
you go on the gym floor.
You may have seen one of these squat bars
before, and you're not quite sure what it
does or why your gym has one. This
is called the safety bar squat rack,
and in this
video,
I'm going to explain to you everything you
need to know.
You do a one-minute version for Instagram.
You do a seven-minute version,
you post it on YouTube.
You then do a written post,
you put it on LinkedIn.
And for the majority of you,
just trust me when I say this, and again,
this is a
video and I've got your best intentions in
heart.
There will be a link in this video for my
PT starter kit that teaches you all the
things about running a business
and making content and all of that. Sure.
Making 500 Instagram posts in the next
three months will do more than anything I
can sell you. Still buy my shit,
but honestly,
500 posts the next three months.
Oh, it seems like a lot. Well,
someone else is going to fucking do those
posts if
you don't. In person,
100 people you approach, four consults,
three clients. And this
is me being kind of optimistic.
Online,
and this is going to depend on how good
your content is, whatever, 1,000
followers, 200 people on your email list.
Out of that, 40 people seeing your offer.
Let's say one person buys.
These businesses run differently.
But if you can understand and learn this,
whatever in-person business you
create over the next fucking whatever many
years, you might start a gym, a cafe, a
fucking jujitsu dojo, whatever it is,
this works.
Then whether you're selling protein
powder, whether you're building a
billion-dollar fucking nootropics brand,
once you understand these two funnels, you
can apply it to whatever you want in life,
and you can absolutely fucking crush
with it. Personal training
is one of the best opportunities in the
world because
the job sucks, the offer's hard,
not many people want it, but you get to
master both sides of the coin of
everything you need to,
to run an online business.
Because the truth is,
I don't really know that much
about the whole thing of business.
I don't know anything about leadership.
I don't know anything about management.
I don't know about any of that stuff.
What I know is how to operate those two
things, and my in-person business
was where
I learned how to run an app
that made over $10 million.
The app that made over $10 million taught
me how to write three number one
bestselling books because I
was using social media with the online
funnel, which
I've now flipped into Nootonic,
which makes millions every single month.
If you told me three years ago I would
have a business worth $100 million, I
wouldn't have believed you.
If you'd gone back three years before
that and told me
I'd have three number one bestselling
author books,
I wouldn't have believed you.
If you went three years before that,
told me that my fitness app would have
made
$10 million, I wouldn't have believed you.
If you went three years before that,
if you told me that I'd be a personal
trainer
and I'd love every single day doing my
job, I wouldn't have believed you.
If you're a personal trainer,
get excited because you have one of the
best
opportunities to run a business
that makes your life drastically better.
But better yet, the thing
that should really excite you
is the lessons you're about
to learn over the next few years
are going to drastically improve the next
10, 20,
30 years of your life. My PT starter kit,
there's a link in the description.
If you want to work with me,
If you're willing to work
and fucking give this your all, the
opportunities are absolutely insane.
And if that doesn't gas you up to do the
work necessary to change your life, well,
then you're probably fucked. And
if that's the case,
don't waste your time watching
this video that I've put here. Bye-bye.